<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Kentoseth - Thoughts on programming, culture, FOSS and more - Islam</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/feeds/islam.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://kentoseth.github.io/</id><updated>2021-10-21T02:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Coding. Culture. Linux. More.</subtitle><entry><title>Poem: Joy and Sorrow</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2021/Oct/21/poem-joy-and-sorrow/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-21T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T02:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2021-10-21:/posts/2021/Oct/21/poem-joy-and-sorrow/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A poem on joy, sorrow and suffering&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I decay,
I watch the world full of joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laughter, pleasure and fun all around,
The orphan, widow and pauper nowhere to be found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The suffering ones are tucked away,
Hidden beneath an extravagant world gone astray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who Hears their suffering except He?
There is a moment where they will find glee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their souls will be dipped for a moment in Heaven,
And they will respond: "Suffering? We cannot remember"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is the world that is temporary,
If you remember this, you are free.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Islam"></category><category term="poetry"></category><category term="love"></category><category term="tasawuf"></category><category term="Allah"></category></entry><entry><title>Poem: When I was alone</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2021/Aug/25/poem-when-i-was-alone/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-25T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-25T02:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2021-08-25:/posts/2021/Aug/25/poem-when-i-was-alone/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A poem on finding Love with the Majestic One&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was alone and had no-one,&lt;br&gt;
I looked into my heart and found The One.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was alone and sought a wife,&lt;br&gt;
He Blessed me with Noor, He Blessed me with life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was alone and searched for a friend,&lt;br&gt;
He was there, without question, without End.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was alone and disobeyed Him,&lt;br&gt;
He still Gave me this Love, and let me write this hymn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am in the grave and all alone,&lt;br&gt;
I hope to smell the fragrance of Jannah and to be comforted under His Throne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the people are all together in Jannah and making merry,&lt;br&gt;
It will only be His Love that my heart will carry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gift of this Love was planted in the heart like a kernel,&lt;br&gt;
Nurture it! Protect it! Grow it! It is a love with One who is Eternal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Islam"></category><category term="poetry"></category><category term="love"></category><category term="tasawuf"></category><category term="Allah"></category></entry><entry><title>Re-ordering the 99 Names of Allah in a poetic form</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2021/Aug/23/re-ordering-the-99-names-of-allah-in-a-poetic-form/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-23T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-23T02:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2021-08-23:/posts/2021/Aug/23/re-ordering-the-99-names-of-allah-in-a-poetic-form/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Re-ordering the 99 Names of Allah in a poetic form to make them easier to memorize or to sing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;بِسْمِ ٱللَّٰهِ ٱلرَّحْمَٰنِ ٱلرَّحِيمِ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.askimam.org/public/question_detail/40862"&gt;99 Names of Allah&lt;/a&gt; are amazing in many ways to me. What I find a bit difficult is committing them to memory. The reason for memorizing them is mentioned from a portion of the Hadith linked above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Indeed, Allah has ninety-nine Names, one hundred less one, whoever counts them shall enter Paradise..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought of devising a way to memorize these Blessed Names by re-ordering the Names in a poetic form so that they can be 'sung' in a manner that makes them easier to memorize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(when I speak of singing here, I refer to it in the capacity of singing a nasheed)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Disrepancy on what the 99 Blessed Names are&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is unanimous agreement that Allah does not have only 99 Names, there is a minor disagreement among different scholars regarding what the 99 Names of Allah are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will not discuss this matter as I am not a Hadith scholar. The references can be read here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hadithanswers.com/the-ninety-nine-names-of-allah-taala/"&gt;Hadith Answers - The ninety nine names of Allah Ta’ala&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ayeina.com/know-allah-better-through-his-names-authentic-list-with-references/"&gt;99 Names of Allah أسماء الحسنى (authentic list with references and resources)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will proceed with the Names listed in the Hadith from at-Tirmidhi. If I am incorrect, may Allah Forgive me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Is this permissible&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sense of caution was observed when considering this idea. I feared that I may be indulging in bid'ah(innovation) with this re-ordering. After consulting with a scholar, he specified that this is not a bid'ah and is perfectly fine to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May Allah Protect him and Protect me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The current order&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure of the 99 Names currently is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;الرَّحْمَنُ الرَّحِيمُ المَلِكُ القُدُّوسُ السَّلَامُ المُؤْمِنُ المُهَيْمِنُ العَزِيزُ الجَبَّارُ المُتَكَبِّرُ الخَالِقُ البَارِئُ المُصَوِّرُ الغَفَّارُ القَهَّارُ الوَهَّابُ الرَّزَّاقُ الفَتَّاحُ العَلِيمُ القَابِضُ البَاسِطُ الخَافِضُ الرَّافِعُ المُعِزُّ المُذِلُّ السَّمِيعُ البَصِيرُ الحَكَمُ العَدْلُ اللَّطِيفُ الخَبِيرُ الحَلِيمُ العَظِيمُ الغَفُورُ الشَّكُورُ العَلِيُّ الكَبِيرُ الحَفِيظُ المُقِيتُ الحَسِيبُ الجَلِيلُ الكَرِيمُ الرَّقِيبُ المُجِيبُ الوَاسِعُ الحَكِيمُ الوَدُودُ المَجِيدُ البَاعِثُ الشَّهِيدُ الحَقُّ الوَكِيلُ القَوِيُّ المَتِينُ الوَلِيُّ الحَمِيدُ المُحْصِي المُبْدِئُ المُعِيدُ المُحْيِي المُمِيتُ الحَيُّ القَيُّومُ الوَاجِدُ المَاجِدُ الوَاحِدُ الصَّمَدُ القَادِرُ المُقْتَدِرُ المُقَدِّمُ المُؤَخِّرُ الأَوَّلُ الآخِرُ الظَّاهِرُ البَاطِنُ الوَالِيَ المُتَعَالِي البَرُّ التَّوَّابُ المُنْتَقِمُ العَفُوُّ الرَّءُوفُ مَالِكُ المُلْكِ ذُو الجَلَالِ وَالإِكْرَامِ، المُقْسِطُ الجَامِعُ الغَنِيُّ المُغْنِي المَانِعُ الضَّارُّ النَّافِعُ النُّورُ الهَادِي البَدِيعُ البَاقِي الوَارِثُ الرَّشِيدُ الصَّبُورُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Poetic re-ordering considerations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first consideration for a poetic structure is Names that use the same vowel(like a kasra) on their middle root and end in the same letter. Examples here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;الرَّحِيمُ  العَلِيمُ الحَلِيمُ العَظِيمُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second consideration would be Names that have the same vowel on their first or middle root letter. The volume of Names that begin with مُ makes this a great example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;المُعِزُّ المُذِلُّ المُحْصِي المُبْدِئُ المُحْيِي المُقْسِطُ المُغْنِي&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These can then be followed by the longer kasra + yaa words like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;المُقِيتُ المُعِيدُ المُمِيتُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another inclusion in the ordering is putting Names next to each other that share similar letters. So if a word ends in a 'ق', then looking for a Name that starts with a 'ق'. If no start/end letters match, then looking for similar letters within each Name and putting them after each other. I have also made sure to not add similar sounding letters in the different words next to each other. Example: البَصِيرُ البَدِيعُ السَّمِيعُ where the 'صِ' and 'سَّ' sound similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal for this further improvement is to add flow to the recital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My structured re-ordering: The 99 Beautiful Names of Allah&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the structure of words that rhyme with each other. I have included stops at appropriate places so that the memorization is easier. Each line end should be considered a stop as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;الرَّحْمَنُ السَّلَامُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;الجَبَّارُ الفَتَّاحُ الغَفَّارُ الرَّزَّاقُ القَهَّارُ الوَهَّابُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;الأَوَّلُ الخَالِقُ الخَافِضُ القَادِرُ القَابِضُ. الضَّارُّ الظَّاهِرُ الرَّافِعُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;البَرُّ البَارِئُ البَاقِي البَاسِطُ البَاطِنُ البَاعِثُ. الوَارِثُ الوَاسِعُ الوَالِيَ الوَاحِدُ الوَاجِدُ المَاجِدُ. الجَامِعُ المَانِعُ النَّافِعُ. التَّوَّابُ الهَادِي الآخِرُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;الحَيُّ القَيُّومُ الرَّءُوفُ الشَّكُورُ الغَفُورُ العَفُوُّ  الوَدُودُ الصَّبُورُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;المَلِكُ الكَرِيمُ الرَّحِيمُ الحَكِيمُ الحَلِيمُ العَلِيمُ العَظِيمُ (49)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;العَزِيزُ العَلِيُّ القَوِيُّ الوَلِيُّ الوَكِيلُ اللَّطِيفُ. الجَلِيلُ المَجِيدُ المَتِينُ الشَّهِيدُ الرَّشِيدُ الرَّقِيبُ. البَصِيرُ البَدِيعُ السَّمِيعُ الحَمِيدُ الحَسِيبُ الحَفِيظُ  الخَبِيرُ الكَبِيرُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;المُتَكَبِّرُ المُصَوِّرُ المُؤَخِّرُ المُهَيْمِنُ المُنْتَقِمُ. المُتَعَالِي المُقْتَدِرُ المُقَدِّمُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;المُؤْمِنُ المُقْسِطُ المُعِزُّ المُذِلُّ. المُحْصِي المُحْيِي المُبْدِئُ المُغْنِي(stop or not)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;المُجِيبُ المُقِيتُ المُمِيتُ المُعِيدُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;العَدْلُ الصَّمَدُ الحَقُّ الحَكَمُ الغَنِيُّ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;النُّورُ القُدُّوسُ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;مَالِكُ المُلْكِ ذُو الجَلَالِ وَالإِكْرَامِ،&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eye of the keen reader should pick up how the structure starts short, gets lengthier towards the middle and culminates in shortness at the end. I take this as inspiration from Allah that it ended up in this structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Memorization technique&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alhamdullilah. I was able to memorize the Names quickly using this new structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My method of learning was outlined above with the stops, but I also learned it line by line and using a singing-type technique as found in the recital of nasheeds or Urdu poems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reader is most welcome to shift the Names within each line to suit their own comforts. I recommend avoiding the shift of the Names into different lines, as this ordering was based on "closest-fit" according to my criteria outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sharing and possible audio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find this re-ordering beneficial and your own Sheikh says it is okay to use it, please consider memorizing it and sharing it. Through His Grace and Mercy, we shall all derive rewards for this effort.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Islam"></category><category term="99"></category><category term="Names"></category><category term="Allah"></category><category term="poetry"></category></entry><entry><title>Couplet: End of Sorrows</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2021/Aug/16/couplet-end-of-sorrows/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-16T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-16T02:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2021-08-16:/posts/2021/Aug/16/couplet-end-of-sorrows/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short couplet on lowering the gaze&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My sorrows seemed many, yet they amounted to just one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By lowering the gaze, so ends the fitna, which appeared like fun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Islam"></category><category term="poetry"></category><category term="couplet"></category><category term="tasawuf"></category></entry><entry><title>Where does sunnah.com get its English Hadith sources?</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2021/May/06/where-does-sunnahcom-get-its-english-hadith-sources/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-06T03:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-06T03:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2021-05-06:/posts/2021/May/06/where-does-sunnahcom-get-its-english-hadith-sources/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tracking down where sunnah.com sources its English translations of Hadiths/Ahadith.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Note to readers: I will use Hadiths instead of Ahadith because it is easier to understand the plural form as Hadiths, instead of Ahadith, for regular readers&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunnah.com is a great website for providing digital copies of the famous &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kutub_al-Sittah"&gt;al-Sahih al-Sittah/Kutub al-Sittah&lt;/a&gt;. For the unaware reader, the Kutub al-Sittah are the 6 famous Hadith books(or collections) that have Hadith compilations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally have issues with the current manner of digitization of classical Islamic works, but I will save that discussion for its own article(where I can go into further detail). The focus of this article is to find the translators and books which are the source material for sunnah.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What sunnah.com says&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at this &lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/about#SourcesNumbering"&gt;sunnah.com - About - Sources&lt;/a&gt;, we can use this as a  starting point to find out where the English content for the Hadiths comes from. This is what the site says regarding English translations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the English we use various translators, a full list of which will appear here shortly inshaAllah. The English has been through two iterations of cleaning (spelling corrections etc.). We have done our best to provide the most authentic and exact hadith possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Sahih Bukhari and Sahih Muslim, the website does provide a reference to an English data source, seen here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bukhari-eng-ref" src="https://kentoseth.github.io/images/sunnahcom/bukhari.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the problem with the "USC-MSA web (English) reference" is that it no longer exists. I tried to figure out what the cause was and apparently it had to do with some political issues raised at the USC, but that is not the concern for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "About" section is also limited on its sources by just saying that they use various translators. We live in an age where many laymen consider themselves capable scholars and use the internet(where sunnah.com ranks highly) to issue fatwas. This makes it even more important that sources are more clearly shown regarding Islamic works and especially their translations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What I found&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the Mercy of Allah and without much looking, I was able to source the English references for most of the Hadith collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kalamullah.com"&gt;Kalamullah&lt;/a&gt; is famous for providing PDFs to various Islamic books, including the 6 Hadith collections(with translations). This is where I was able to make the connection back to sunnah.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at &lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/ibnmajah/1/200"&gt;ibn Majah - Book 1 - Hadith 200&lt;/a&gt;, the Arabic and English references are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;English translation    : Vol. 1, Book 1, Hadith 466
Arabic reference   : Book 1, Hadith 503&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book to download is &lt;a href="https://kalamullah.com/Books/Hadith/Sunan%20Ibn%20Majah%20Vol.%201%20-%201-802.pdf"&gt;ibn Majah Volume 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what sunnah.com says in English for Hadith 200:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was narrated that Qais bin Sa'd said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The Prophet came to us and we gave him water to perform a bath." Then we brought him a Warshiyyah cloth, and he wrapped himself in it. It is as if I can see the marks of the Wars on the folds of his stomach."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what the PDF shows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Majah-1" src="https://kentoseth.github.io/images/sunnahcom/majah1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word-for-word, it is the same content. I tested this out randomly in 4 other places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/ibnmajah:750"&gt;ibn Majah - Hadith 750&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol1 pg. 492&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/ibnmajah:750"&gt;ibn Majah - Hadith 1785&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol3 pg. 19 (I found a missing word on the website, but the English content is almost exactly the same)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/ibnmajah:2415"&gt;ibn Majah - Hadith 2415&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol3 pg. 382&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/ibnmajah:4056"&gt;ibn Majah - Hadith 4056&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol5 pg. 246&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author and publisher of this version is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Publisher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Maktaba&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Dar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Salam&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Published&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2007&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ISBN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;9960&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;9881&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Ahadith&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;edited&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;researched&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;referenced&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Hafiz&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Abu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Tahir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Zubair&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Ali Za&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Translated&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Nasiruddin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;al&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Khattab&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Canada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Edited&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Huda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Khattab&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Canada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Abu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Khaliyl&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will apply the same method(but reducing to 3 Hadiths per set) for the other 5 Hadith collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Bukhari&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volumes to download for this set are here: &lt;a href="https://kalamullah.com/sahih-bukhari.html"&gt;Sahih Bukhari&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/bukhari:61"&gt;Bukhari - Hadith 61&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol1 pg. 89 (Book3, CH4, nr. 61)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/bukhari:1200"&gt;Bukhari - Hadith 1200&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol2 pg. 175 (Book21, CH2, nr. 1200) - not a word-for-word match, small editing for spelling/grammar improvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/bukhari:6290"&gt;Bukhari - Hadith 6290&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol8 pg. 173 (Book79, CH47, nr. 6290)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author and publisher of this version is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Publisher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Maktaba&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Dar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;us&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Salam&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;same&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ibn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Majah&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;books&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Published&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1997&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ISBN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;9960&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;717&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;31&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Translated&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Dr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Muhammad&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Muhsin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Khan&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Muslim&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volumes to download for this set are here: &lt;a href="https://kalamullah.com/sahih-muslim.html"&gt;Sahih Muslim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/muslim:55a"&gt;Muslim - Hadith 55a&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol1 pg. 150 (Book1, CH23, nr. 196) - not a word-for-word match, some changes present(common folk -&amp;gt; masses)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/muslim:900"&gt;Muslim - Hadith 900&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol2 pg. 422 (Book9, CH4, nr. 2087) - also not a word-for-word match&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/muslim:2035"&gt;Muslim - Hadith 2035a&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol5 pg. 383 (Book36, CH18, nr. 2035) - CH heading the same but significant variation in Hadith text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author and publisher used for Sahih Muslim on sunnah.com is presumably not the same as the version available on kalamullah.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;an-Nasa'i&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volumes to download for this set are here: &lt;a href="https://kalamullah.com/sunan-an-nasai.html"&gt;Sunan An-Nasa'i&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/nasai:691"&gt;Nasai - Hadith 691&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol1 pg. 408 (Book8, CH4, nr. 691)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/nasai:1300"&gt;Nasai - Hadith 1300&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol2 pg. 260 (Book13, CH58, nr. 1301)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/nasai:691"&gt;Nasai - Hadith 691&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol1 pg. 408 (Book8, CH4, nr. 691)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author and publisher of this version is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Publisher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Maktaba&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Dar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;us&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Salam&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;same&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ibn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Majah&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;books&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Published&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2007&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ISBN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;978&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;9960&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;58&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;760&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Ahadith&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;edited&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;referenced&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Hafiz&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Abu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Tahir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Zubair&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Ali Za&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Translated&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Nasiruddin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;al&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Khattab&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Canada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Edited&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Huda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Khattab&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Canada&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Abu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Khaliyl&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Abu Dawood&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volumes to download for this set are here: &lt;a href="https://kalamullah.com/sunan-abu-dawood.html"&gt;Sunan Abu Dawood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/abudawud:376"&gt;Abu Dawood - Hadith 376&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol1 pg. 237 (Book1, CH135, nr. 376) - translation appears to be different(same meaning, different translation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/abudawud:1623"&gt;Abu Dawood - Hadith 1623&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol2 pg. 280 (Book9, CH22, nr. 1623) - translation appears to be different(same meaning, different translation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/abudawud:3502"&gt;Abu Dawood - Hadith 3502&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol4 pg. 139 (Book22, CH67, nr. 3502) - translation appears to be different(same meaning, different translation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author and publisher used for Sahih Muslim on sunnah.com is presumably not the same as the version available on kalamullah.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;at-Tirmidhi&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volumes to download for this set are here: &lt;a href="https://kalamullah.com/jami-at-tirmidhi.html"&gt;Jami' At-Tirmidhi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/tirmidhi:601"&gt;Tirmidhi - Hadith 601&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol2 pg. 63 (Book(*), CH68, nr. 601)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/tirmidhi:1461"&gt;Tirmidhi - Hadith 1461&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol3 pg. 246 (Book15, CH28, nr. 1461)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunnah.com/tirmidhi:2168"&gt;Tirmidhi - Hadith 2168&lt;/a&gt; - PDF Vol4 pg. 408 (Book31, CH8, nr. 2168)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*The discrepancy in Book numbers appears in Vol2, where "Travelling" and "Fasting" were not given Book numbers and hence the online version is 2 Books ahead of the PDFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author and publisher of this version is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Publisher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Maktaba&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Dar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;us&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Salam&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;same&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ibn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Majah&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;books&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Published&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2007&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ISBN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;978&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;9960&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;9967&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;38&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Ahadith&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;edited&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;referenced&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Hafiz&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Abu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Tahir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Zubair&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Ali Za&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Translated&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Abu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Khaliyl&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;review&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Islamic&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Research&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Section&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Darussalam&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sahih Muslim and Sunan Abu Dawood were the only 2 using different Arabic-English translations. I am aware that other translations of some of the Hadith collections do exist, but the slant of sunnah.com appears to be towards the Saudi Arabian publisher Darus Salam. It might be that the sources for Sahih Muslim and Sunan Abu Dawood are also by Darus Salam, but from different authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any mistakes were made in this article, please contact me to have them fixed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Islam"></category><category term="hadith"></category><category term="isnad"></category><category term="sunnahcom"></category><category term="english"></category></entry><entry><title>Lists of early Islamic scholars who learned from each other</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2021/Feb/19/lists-of-early-islamic-scholars-who-learned-from-each-other/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-19T02:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T02:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2021-02-19:/posts/2021/Feb/19/lists-of-early-islamic-scholars-who-learned-from-each-other/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A bunch of lists highlighting who learned from who from the early scholar of Islam&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When browsing Wikipedia and looking up names of well-known classical Islamic scholars, the information on them is sparse in some regards. Who they learned from and who they taught is fundamental to how Islamic knowledge is passed down and is known as 'isnad'(chain - sometimes referred as "chain of narrators").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read a book called "Four Illustrious Imams" written by Maulana Makbool Ahmed Suharwi and translated by Mufti Afzel Hossen Elias that provides some of the lists we are looking for. I will reproduce them as per the book(see the last portion "Ilmi Chart").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Twelve Renowned Jurists amongst the Sahaba(RA)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Mu'aadh bin Jabal(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Ubayy bin Ka'b(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Abu Dardaa(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Abdullah bin Mas'ood(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Zaid bin Thaabit(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Ali(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Uthmaan(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Abu Moosa Ash'ari(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Jaabir(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Abdullah bin Umar(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Abdullah bin Abbaas(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Mu'aawiya(RA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Imam Abu Haneefa(ra) learned Hadith from&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Ataa(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Naafi(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Abdur Rahmaan bin Hurmuzaan(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Salma bint Kuhail(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Baaqir(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Qataadah(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Amr bin Dinaar(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Narrators of Hadith from Imam Abu Haneefa(ra)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Wakee(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Yazeed bin Haaroon(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Sa'd bin Silt(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Abu Aasim(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Abdur Razzaaq bin Humaam(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Ubaidullah bin Moosa(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Studied Hadith from Imam Abu Haneefa(ra)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Yahya bin Sa'eed Qattaan(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Wakee bin Jarraa(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Sufyaan bin Uyayna(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Abdullah bin Mubaarak(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Abdur Razzaaq bin Humaam(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Yazeed bin Haaroon(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Hafs bin Ghayaath(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Yahya bin Zakariyya(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Studied Fiqh from Imam Abu Haneefa(ra)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Abdullah bin Mubaarak(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Yahya bin Sa'eed Qattaan(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Wakee bin Jarraa(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Sufyaan bin Uyayna(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Yazeed bin Haaroon(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Hafs bin Ghayaath(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Yahya bin Abi Zaa'idah(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Imam Abu Yusuf(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Imam Zufar bin Hudhail(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Imam Muhammed bin Hasan Shaybaani(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Imam Muhammed bin Hasan Shaybaani(ra) narrated Hadith from&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadhrat Mas'ar bin Kudaam(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Imam Abu Haneefa(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Zufar bin Hudhail(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Awzaa'ee(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Sufyaan Thowri(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Maalik bin Dinaar(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Maalik bin Anas(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Abu Yusuf(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ten Distinguished Mujtahideen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Ja'far bin Muhammed(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Sufyaan Thowri(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Maalik bin Anas(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Awzaa'ee(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Laith bin Sa'd Misri(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Shaafi'ee(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Ishaaq bin Raahway(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Ahmed bin Hambal(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Bukhaari(Muhammed bin Isma'eel)(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imam Muslim(ra)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Islam"></category><category term="scholars"></category><category term="hanafi"></category><category term="isnad"></category><category term="sahaba"></category></entry></feed>