<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Kentoseth - Thoughts on programming, culture, FOSS and more - Other</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/feeds/other.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://kentoseth.github.io/</id><updated>2021-10-22T03:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Coding. Culture. Linux. More.</subtitle><entry><title>Blog Updates: Newsletter and backups</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2021/Oct/22/blog-updates-newsletter-and-backups/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-22T03:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-22T03:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2021-10-22:/posts/2021/Oct/22/blog-updates-newsletter-and-backups/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Adding a newsletter to the blog and creating backups of this website for content preservation&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;بِسْمِ ٱللَّٰهِ ٱلرَّحْمَٰنِ ٱلرَّحِيمِ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have made a few improvements to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog remains tracker-free. This means no analytics or even pixel-trackers. Only my free hosting provider has knowledge of the blog analytics and this is something not worth paying for(there are too many 'free' static hosts now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Newsletter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have added a newsletter using &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com"&gt;Tinyletter&lt;/a&gt;. You can subscribe &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/Kentoseth"&gt;HERE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newsletter is an alternative for people who don't use or don't know how to use RSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't personally subscribe to newsletters because of the "monetize everything" mentality of the modern world. Rest assured that this blog will remain focused on the content and not on shilling. Insha Allah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Backups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I will inevitably pass on, I don't expect those around me to carry the burden of renewing my domain name. I have come up with a mechanism to preserve my blog content using both GitHub(https://kentoseth.github.io) and GitLab(https://kentoseth.gitlab.io). These backups are based on the assumption that GitHub and GitLab will act in good faith to keep the backups preserved and that they will outlive me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also the discussion around making a Pelican blog multi-publish can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican/issues/2894"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the Internet Archive, there is no way to make it index your website. The crawlers work on their own unknown mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The many P2P and blockchain options are not workable/feasible either and have their own bus factors. Expecting someone to keep your RaspBerry Pi running for a &lt;a href="https://zeronet.io"&gt;ZeroNet website&lt;/a&gt; is less practical than just renewing a domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also expended too much energy looking for a cheap/free/practical option and the closest I got was to just create backups on GitHub/GitLab and any other provider that has a similar "free static website" feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Publishing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also recently had 1 of my articles published by another blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article can be found here: &lt;a href="https://arabic-for-nerds.com/sources-of-sunnah-com-and-shamela-ws/"&gt;What are the sources of sunnah.com and shamela.ws?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Social Media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not use social media out of principle, due to its invasive privacy violations. I have however, setup a Mastodon account on &lt;a href="https://fosstodon.org/about"&gt;Fosstodon&lt;/a&gt; as it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;runs on Open Source software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is 1 of the few Mastodon instances with a reliable longevity plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is based around FOSS(Free and Open Source Software)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can follow me at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosstodon.org/@kentoseth"&gt;https://fosstodon.org/@kentoseth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any suggestions for improving this blog(layout, reach, etc.), reach out to me via the email on the left.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Other"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="email"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="backup"></category></entry><entry><title>Expanding Blog Scope</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2020/Oct/10/expanding-blog-scope/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-10T03:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T03:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2020-10-10:/posts/2020/Oct/10/expanding-blog-scope/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blogging about other topics of interest outside the technology scope&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I initially planned on maintaining this blog with a focus on just technology-related topics like programming and Information Security(InfoSec). As my interests have evolved(possibly due to age?) and my unwillingness to maintain multiple different blogs that focus on other areas of interest, I have decided to expand this personal blog to talk about other interesting phenomenon relative to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 key topics I have found worthy of blogging about are: culture and languages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Languages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I start with languages because I have taken up the effort to learn a new language(Arabic) and I have also been learning "how to learn a new language". There is a lot to be said about this and I plan to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also found that textual preservation of my home-language(&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memoni_language"&gt;Memon&lt;/a&gt;) is in short supply online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noting the shortage of textual preservation of my home-language(above), there is also a shortage of preservation of the cultural habits of the Memon people. As South African Memons, we have also diverged quite a bit from our counterparts in India/UK/Malawi/Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing broader culturally-Memon topics and the South African divergence will be a great lesson in introspection and possibly bias too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also hope to increase my frequency of blogging and speak about other topics of interest. "Lifehacks", like my article about &lt;a href="https://kentoseth.tk/2019/Mar/17/rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack/#rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack"&gt;Rechargeable batteries(AA/AAA)&lt;/a&gt;, will also appear occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also plan to continue blogging about technology, but after 6+ years of &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, technology-blogging can feel 'stale' at times.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Other"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="languages"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="ideas"></category><category term="thoughts"></category></entry><entry><title>Rechargeable battery(AA/AAA) hack</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2019/Mar/17/rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-17T03:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-03-17T03:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Moe. H</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2019-03-17:/posts/2019/Mar/17/rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A simple hack to recharge your rechargeable batteries in electronic devices&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been using a wireless-mouse for a long time now. Instead of buying expensive single-use batteries, I decided I would use some spare AAA rechargeable batteries I had laying around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't own a recharging-device for the batteries though. However, my cordless housephone/landline also uses the same size batteries as the wireless-mouse. With this convenience, I now recharge my batteries using the cordless housephone and don't need to buy a specific recharging-device for the batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will save you time(finding where you left the recharging-device) and money(buying a single-use electronic item). You may also find this solution convenient, as you will own 1 less electronic item. Also worth a mention that this type of "hack" is so intuitive that people may overlook it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Other"></category><category term="battery"></category><category term="batteries"></category><category term="AA"></category><category term="AAA"></category><category term="rechargeable"></category><category term="hacks"></category></entry></feed>