<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Kentoseth - Thoughts on programming, culture, FOSS and more - Other</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/feeds/other.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://kentoseth.github.io/</id><updated>2020-10-10T03:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Coding. Culture. Linux. More.</subtitle><entry><title>Expanding Blog Scope</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2020/Oct/10/expanding-blog-scope/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-10T03:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T03:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Mohamed H.</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2020-10-10:/posts/2020/Oct/10/expanding-blog-scope/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blogging about other topics of interest outside the technology scope&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I initially planned on maintaining this blog with a focus on just technology-related topics like programming and Information Security(InfoSec). As my interests have evolved(possibly due to age?) and my unwillingness to maintain multiple different blogs that focus on other areas of interest, I have decided to expand this personal blog to talk about other interesting phenomenon relative to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 key topics I have found worthy of blogging about are: culture and languages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Languages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I start with languages because I have taken up the effort to learn a new language(Arabic) and I have also been learning "how to learn a new language". There is a lot to be said about this and I plan to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also found that textual preservation of my home-language(&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memoni_language"&gt;Memon&lt;/a&gt;) is in short supply online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noting the shortage of textual preservation of my home-language(above), there is also a shortage of preservation of the cultural habits of the Memon people. As South African Memons, we have also diverged quite a bit from our counterparts in India/UK/Malawi/Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing broader culturally-Memon topics and the South African divergence will be a great lesson in introspection and possibly bias too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also hope to increase my frequency of blogging and speak about other topics of interest. "Lifehacks", like my article about &lt;a href="https://kentoseth.tk/2019/Mar/17/rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack/#rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack"&gt;Rechargeable batteries(AA/AAA)&lt;/a&gt;, will also appear occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also plan to continue blogging about technology, but after 6+ years of &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, technology-blogging can feel 'stale' at times.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Other"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="languages"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="ideas"></category><category term="thoughts"></category></entry><entry><title>Rechargeable battery(AA/AAA) hack</title><link href="https://kentoseth.github.io/posts/2019/Mar/17/rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-17T03:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-03-17T03:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Moe. H</name></author><id>tag:kentoseth.github.io,2019-03-17:/posts/2019/Mar/17/rechargeable-batteryaaaaa-hack/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A simple hack to recharge your rechargeable batteries in electronic devices&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been using a wireless-mouse for a long time now. Instead of buying expensive single-use batteries, I decided I would use some spare AAA rechargeable batteries I had laying around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't own a recharging-device for the batteries though. However, my cordless housephone/landline also uses the same size batteries as the wireless-mouse. With this convenience, I now recharge my batteries using the cordless housephone and don't need to buy a specific recharging-device for the batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will save you time(finding where you left the recharging-device) and money(buying a single-use electronic item). You may also find this solution convenient, as you will own 1 less electronic item. Also worth a mention that this type of "hack" is so intuitive that people may overlook it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Other"></category><category term="battery"></category><category term="batteries"></category><category term="AA"></category><category term="AAA"></category><category term="rechargeable"></category><category term="hacks"></category></entry></feed>